Register of the Ivo Čičin-Šain Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Ivo Čičin-Šain papers
1920-1980
2011C8
Čičin-Šain, Ivo, 1897-1974.
2 manuscript boxes (0.6 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
The papers contain records from the Yugoslav government-in-exile, including financial records for the period 1941-1949 that document government personnel and office expenses, and Čićin-Šain's role as Minister of Finance. Materials also include documents on the court trial brought by Ivo Čičin-Šain against Keable (Press) Limited, publisher of the British Communist Party newspaper Daily Worker, and Čićin-Šain's post-war activities in Yugoslav émigré affairs.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2011.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical/Historical Note
7 October 1897 Born, Vodice, Croatia
1913 Graduated from the Commercial College "Mahr" in Ljubljana, Slovenia
1915 Served in the Austrian Army holding various offices and hospital duties
1919 Worked for Export-Import d.d., Split, Croatia
1921 Joined Vestra Trading Co., Inc. branch in Split, Croatia
1923 General manager of Vestra Inc., Split, Croatia
1930 Employed by the First Dalmatian People's Bank, Split, Croatia
1932 Opened a new firm, The Šain and Co., Split, Croatia
1941 Loyal to the Royal Yugoslav government-in-exile. Financially assisted the Yugoslav Army under the command of General Draža Mihailović
May 1943 Formed the resistance organisation "National Committee of Dalmatia"
Beginning of October 1943 Escaped from occupied Yugoslavia to Cairo, Egypt
16 October 1943 Appointed Minister of Finance, trade and industry, Royal Yugoslav government-in exile
November 1943 Resigned due to working conditions in Cairo, Egypt; his resignation was not accepted, and he remained Minister of Finance
21 December 1943-5 May 1944 Daily Worker, the Londoner Communist paper, published allegations that Čićin-Šain trafficked goods with the enemy
1944 Ivo Čičin-Šain vs. Keable (Press) Limited, publisher of the British Communist Party newspaper Daily Worker
24 Feb 1944 Arrived in London
18 April 1944 Dismissed as Minister of Finance of Royal Yugoslav government in exile, due to his health
1951 Emigrated to the U.S.; active in post-war Yugoslav émigré affairs
Scope and Content of Collection
The papers contain records from the Yugoslav government-in-exile, including financial records for the period 1941-1949 that document government personnel and office expenses, and Čićin-Šain's role as Minister of Finance. Materials also include documents on the court trial brought by Ivo Čičin-Šain against Keable (Press) Limited, publisher of the British Communist Party newspaper Daily Worker, and Čićin-Šain's post-war activities in Yugoslav émigré affairs. The photographs depict the Royal Yugoslav family of Petar II.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into five series, Yugoslav government-in-exile financial records, Ivo Čićin-Šain vs. Keable (Press) Limited legal materials, Postwar Yugoslav émigré affairs materials, Biographical file, and Photographs.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
World War, 1939-1945--Yugoslavia.; World War, 1939-1945--Governments in exile.; World War, 1939-1945--Diplomatic history.; Yugoslavia--History--Axis occupation, 1941-1945.; Yugoslavia--Emigration and immigration.
Collection Contents
- Yugoslav government-in-exile financial records, 1941-1949. (Box 1)
  Consists of reports, financial records, lists, and clippings. Arranged by document type
  - Personnel and office expenses, October 1943., Includes personnel payroll documents, and list of Embassy offices by location (Folder 1: 1)
  - Ministry of Finance office file, 1941-1945 (Box 1)
    - General correspondence, 1943-1945 (Folder 1: 2)
    - Financial records, 1943-1944 (Folder 1: 3-4)
    - Official Gazette of the Kingdom of Yugoslavia extract, 1941-1944 (Folder 1: 5)
  - Reports, speeches, 1943-1949 (Folder 1: 6)
  - Military-Medical Supply reports, 1942-1944. (Folder 1: 7)
  - Yugoslav Red Cross Society materials, London, 1942-1944 (Folder 1: 8)
- Ivo Čićin-Šain vs. Keable (Press) Limited legal materials, 1941-1950. (Box 1)
  Includes legal correspondence with Daily Worker publisher Keable (Press) Limited, depositions and reports. Arranged by document type
  - Thomas Cooper and Co., Keable (Press) Correspondence, 1944-1950 (Folder 1: 9)
  - Depositions, legal documents, and correspondence with Keable (Press) Limited, 1943-1948 (Folder 1: 10)
  - Yugoslav government officials' reports regarding Čićin-Šain activities, 1942-1944 (Folder 1: 11)
- Yugoslav émigré affairs materials, 1942-1980. (Box 1-2)
  Includes correspondence with Yugoslav émigrés, a leaflet, a pamphlet, clippings, newspapers, and writings. Arranged by document type
  - Correspondence between Yugoslav government officials and Čićin Šain, 1943-1947 (Folder 1: 12)
  - Dalmatian Club materials, 1952 (Folder 2: 1)
    Correspondence, speeches and documents referring to the Yugoslav emigrants' efforts to form a club
  - Newsletters, clippings, writings, 1942-1980. (Folder 2: 2)
    News on the situation in Yugoslavia and reports on the Yugoslav emigrants' activities published by Jerićeve Sviće, Dalmatian Publishing Company
- Biographical file, 1920-1975. (Box 2)
  Includes biography, personal correspondence, certificates, invitations, business cards, a leaflet, a pamphlet, and clippings
  - Personal documents and correspondence, 1920-1975. (Folder 2: 3)
    Includes a biography, personal correspondence, certificates, invitations, business cards, a leaflet, a pamphlet, clippings, government stationery
- Photographs, 1940-1951. (Folder 2: 4)
  Consists of prints depicting Petar II and his family
  - Portrait of Petar II, King of Yugoslavia, circa 1940
  - Petar II, King of Yugoslavia wedding, 1944
  - Petar II, King of Yugoslavia with Queen Alexandra and Prince Alexander, 1947
  - Portraits of Prince Alexander, 1948 and 1951